Guide to the Frank Moore Papers, 1971-2003 MSS.135
Fales Library and Special Collections
Frank Moore Papers
1971-2003
Fales Library and Special Collections
Moore, Frank, 1953-2002
MSS.135
44.75 Linear Feet in 57 boxes and 3 flat file folders
The Frank Moore Papers document the professional career of the artist and activist, Frank Moore. Materials include notebooks, correspondence, administrative files, source materials for his work, production materials for 2 of Moore's collaborative film projects, as well as his personal library. Strengths of this collection include Moore's sketchbooks and notebooks and the meticulous documentation Moore maintained of his artistic output, including the film projects, "Beehive" and "The Miller's Wife".
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Frank Moore Papers were donated to the Fales Library and Special Collections by the Gesso Foundation in 2003. In July 2020, Patrick Orton donated an accretion to the collection; the accession number associated with this addition is 2020.033.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Frank Moore (1953-2002) is best known for his hyperrealist symbolic paintings that address junctures between social, environmental, medical, and scientific issues. Through painting Moore explored the dissonance between the medical benefits of genetic engineering and the ecological costs. He combined these themes with a painting style that favored bright colors and magical realism. In addition, Moore created intricate frames to complement the paintings. For example, the Niagara paintings have frames of piping and spigots referencing the re-routing of the water to a hydroelectric power plant as well as human consumption of polluted water. These characteristics lead The New York Times to describe Frank Moore as "a painter and AIDS activist whose jewel-like allegories brought beauty and bite to the themes of scientific progress, environmental pollution and the medical establishment."
Frank Moore was born on June 22, 1953 in New York City. He grew up on Long Island and in the Adirondacks, his childhood summer home. In 1970, at the age of 17 he attended the Haystack Mountain School of Crafts in Deer Isle, Maine. In 1975 he graduated from Yale University with honors and a degree in art and psychology. After college he moved to New York City, where he studied decorative art materials and techniques while working at the Isabel O'Neil School of the Painted Finish. In 1977 he received a two-year residency at the Cité Internationale des Arts in Paris, France. When he returned to New York in 1979 he began designing sets and costumes for the choreographer Jim Self. Their collaboration lasted until the late 1980's and included several dance-based experimental films such as "Beehive", which won a Bessie in 1985. Moore created set designs and costumes for numerous theatrical and dance companies and performances including the Joffrey Ballet. Through these films and performances Moore explored themes of jealousy, passion and the supernatural in combination with his fascination with nature and the environment.
Moore's first one-person exhibition was in 1983 at The Clocktower in Tribeca. In 1992, Moore was selected to be represented by Sperone Westwater, a prominent NYC gallery. In 1995 his work was selected to be exhibited in the Whitney Museum of American Art Biennial. Moore's work is included in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Albright Knox Art Gallery and the New York Public Library. Moore was also the recipient of numerous awards and grants including the National Endowment for the Arts, New York State Council on the Arts, the Jerome Foundation, and Art Matters. In 1999 he received the Academy Award in Art from the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Moore continues to be represented by the Sperone Westwater Gallery in New York.
Moore was a key player in several AIDS organizations and art related projects including Visual AIDS, the artists' faction of ACT UP. While working with the group in 1991, Moore played a significant role in creating the AIDS red ribbon. The accessory helped raise a great deal of public awareness about AIDS and a great deal of money to fight AIDS as well as inspiring similar ribbons in other colors for other causes. Moore was also instrumental in the development of the Estate Project which works to document and preserve works created by people with AIDS in all artistic disciplines.
Prior to his death in April 2002, Frank Moore established the Gesso Foundation (www.gesso.org). Through this organization Moore ensured that his artwork continues to impact discourse on the environment and social issues. His life and his vision are contained within the organization's mission statement, "Frank Moore established the Gesso Foundation to place his art for maximum public benefit, and to support organizations concerned with the arts, social justice, environmental and AIDS-related causes."
One Person Exhibitions
1983, "The Birds and the Bees," The Clocktower, New York (paintings)
1984, "Recent Paintings," Christminster Gallery, New York
1985, "Drawings for the Theater," Abbaye Royale a Fontevraud, France
1988, "Recent Paintings," Paula Allen Gallery, New York
1989, "Recent Paintings," Paula Allen Gallery, New York
1990, "Recent Paintings," Paula Allen Gallery, New York
1993, Sperone Westwater, New York, 9 - 30 January
1995, Sperone Westwater, New York, 25 March - 22 April (catalogue)
1996, "Nature/Culture and the postmodern Sublime," Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, NY, 13-28 April
1996, Galleria Gian Enzo Sperone, Rome, November-December (catalogue)
1998 Sperone Westwater, New York, 28 March-25 April (catalogue)
2002-03 "Frank Moore, Green Thumb in a Dark Eden," Orlando Museum of Art, Orlando, FL and Albright-Knox Art Gallery, Buffalo, NY (catalogue)
2003 "Frank Moore," Sperone Westwater, 12 September- 25 October
Selected Group Exhibitions, Film Screenings and Theater Work
1979
Poetry Room, P.S. 1 Museum, Long Island City, Queens. Curated by Steve Hamilton. Exhibition includes a book collaboration with poet Brad Gooch and designer Laurie Hastreiter, produced at the Cite Internationale des Arts, Paris, France.
1980
Watercolor Show, P.S. 1 Museum, Long Island City, Queens. Curated by Donald Droll
Childhood Show, Jungle Red Studios, New York. curated by Allan Frame
Summer Invitational, The Drawing Center, New York
"Domestic Interlude," "Uproots," "Marking Time," and "Scraping Bottoms," (Collaboration with Jim Self) Presented at: The Cunningham Studio, June; Dance Theater Workshop, October; The Whitney Downtown, September; The Grey Gallery, December; Moming, December.
"Domestic Interlude," "Uproots," "Marking Time," and "Scraping Bottoms," (Collaboration with Jim Self) Presented at: The Cunningham Studio, June; Dance Theater Workshop, October; The Whitney Downtown, September; The Grey Gallery, December; Moming, December.
1981
Frank Moore and George Negroponte, Brooke Alexander, New York
Blacklight Show, Club 57, New York
Erotic Art Show, Club 57, New York
7/3/7, White Columns, New York, curated by Ted Greenwald
Lower Manhattan Drawing Show, Mudd Club, New York, curated by Keith Haring
New York/New Wave, P.S. 1 Museum, Long Island City, Queens, curated by Diego Cortez
"Blue Grotto," (collaboration with Jim Self and Ellen Kogan) commissioned by the Jacobs Pillow Dance Festival, Lennox, Mass. premiered in July
"Scraping Bottoms," program (collaboration with Jim Self) presented at the American Center, Paris, France in June and at the Holland Dance Festival
1982
Beasts, Institute for Art and Urban Resources (P.S.1) Long Island City, Queens
Selections, Artists Space, New York
Crosscurrents, Aaron Berman Gallery, New York
New Drawing in America, The Drawing Center, New York
"Blue Grotto," presented at the Riverside Dance Festival in May (collaboration with Jim Self and Ellen Kogan)
Broccoli, La Mamounia, and Poverty in the Penthouse, theater collaboration with John Heys and Butch Walker presented at the Open Gate Theater, New York
1983
Art on Paper, Weatherspoon Gallery, Greensboro, N.C.
Summer Group Show, John Weber Gallery, New York
New York Work, Studio 10, Chur, Switzerland and Keltenkeller, Zurich, Switzerland
"Beehive pas de Deux," (collaboration with Jim Self) presented at the Kitchen in May
1984
Private Mythologies, P.S. 122, New York
Summer Group Show, Cable Gallery, New York
Artists Design for the Theater, Phillippe Bonnafont Gallery, San Francisco, CA.
Lower East Side Galleries, Artist Space, New York
1985
Artists in the Theater, BACA Downtown, Brooklyn, NY
"Beehive," film shown at the Brooklyn Academy of Music (Bessie Award), at the Public Theater, N.Y., at the Cinemateque Francaise, Paris, France; and as part of an Asian Tour of films from the Cinematheque collection organized by Patrick Bonsard.
"Beehive," film and Ballet commissioned by the Centre National de Danse Contemporaine d'Angers, France, premiering in June
1986
In Black and White, Ted Greenwald Gallery, New York
Dike Blair, Paul McMahon, Frank Moore, Christminster Gallery, New York
Twelve in New York, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
"Splatter," (collaboration with Charles Moulton), presented at P.S. 122, New York
1987
Unreal: Conceptual Realism, Alexander Wood Gallery, New York
"Beehive" Ballet commissioned by the Boston Ballet; a collaboration with Jim Self and Scott Johnson, which premiered at the Wang Center, Boston, in March
"The Miller's Wife" film production and performance in residence at P.S. 1, Queens, September - December
"Camellia" (collaboration with Jim Self and A. Leroy) presented at the Dance Theater Workshop in April, premiered at the Bama Theater, Tuscaloosa Alabama, in April
"Beehive" film shown at the Shakespeare Theater, Boston
"Beehive" also shown at the Dance on Camera Festival, Donnell Film Library, New York, and on Alabama Public T.V.
1988
"Crankhouse" and "Beehive" (Dance/Theater work and film) presented at the Upstate of the Arts Festival, Binghampton, N.Y.
"Crankhouse" (collaboration with Jim Self) premieres at Dance Theater Workshop, New York
"Beehive" film presented at Moming, Chicago, and at the United States Film Festival, Provo, Utah
1988-1990
Panelist, Visual Artists Program, New York State Council on the Arts
1989
The City/The Spirit, exhibition curated by Ken Tisa at the Paula Allen Gallery, New York
"Beehive" film shown at the Film Forum, New York, December and on "Eye on Dance," Channel 13, New York
Panelist, Film Program, New York State Council on the Arts
Panelist, Film Program, New York State Council on the Arts
1990
Work on Paper, Paula Allen Gallery, New York
Art as Object/ Object as Art, Springs Art Gallery, East Hampton, N.Y.
"Offstage Attitudes," curator -- exhibition of art by performance artists held at Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, Alice Tully hall, as part of the "Serious Fun!" Festival
"Ball Passing," collaboration with Charles Moulton for the Joffrey Ballet to premier at Lincoln Center (The New York State Theater) in March, 1991
"Ball Passing," collaboration with Charles Moulton for the Joffrey Ballet to premier at Lincoln Center (The New York State Theater) in March, 1991
1990 Portrait Show, P.S. 122 Gallery, New York
AIDS Forum, Artist Space, New York
SAFE Portfolio, print commissioned by Manhattan Borough President Ruth Messinger to benefit the Special Arts Fund For Emergencies.
Panelist, Theater Program, New York State Council on the Arts
Member, Steering Committee, AIDS Working Group, National Endowment for the Arts
1991
Panelist, Theater Program, New York State Council on the Arts
Panelist, Policy Retreat at Snug Harbor, New York State Council on the Arts
Lecturer, The School of Visual Arts
1992-1994
From Media to Metaphor--Art about AIDS, Independent Curators Inc., show curated by Thomas Sokolowski and Robert Atkins. Travelling to: Emerson Gallery, Hamilton College, Clinton, NY; Center on Contemporary Art, Seattle, WA.; Kutztown University, Kutztown, PA.; Musee d'Art Contemporain de Montreal, Montreal, Quebec, Canada; Bass Museum of Art, Miami Beach, Fl.; McKissisk Museum, The University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina; Fine Art Gallery, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana; Santa Barbara Contemporary Arts Forum, Santa Barbara, CA.; Grey Art Gallery and Study Center, New York University, New York (catalogue)
Slow Art, Institute for Art and Urban Resources, Long Island City, Queens, N.Y. (curated by Alanna Heiss)
Private Public, Betty Rymer Gallery, The School of the Art Institute of Chicago, Chicago IL.
Board Member, Visual AIDS
"Day Without Art, December 1, 1992," poster design for Visual AIDS Artist's Caucus
1993
"The Spirit of Drawing," Sperone Westwater, 121 Greene St., New York, 1 May - 12 June
1993-1994
"Thema: AIDS," Henie-Onstad Kunstsenter, Oslo, Norway, 8 May - 20 June, 1993; and travelled to: Bergens Kunstforening, Bergen, Norway; Karl Ernst Osthaus-Museum, Hagen, The Netherlands, 30 November 1993 - 9 January 1994. (catalogue)
"The Figure as Fiction," The Contemporary Arts Center, Cincinnati, OH., 4 December 1993 - 23 January 1994. (catalogue)
1994
"Fallen Idylls: American Figurative Painting," Art Miami '94, International Art Exposition, Miami, January 5 - 9; and The Cultural Center of the Martin County Council for the Arts, Stuart, Florida, January 14 - March 1 1994.
"Fallen Idylls: American Figurative Painting," Art Miami '94, International Art Exposition, Miami, January 5 - 9; and The Cultural Center of the Martin County Council for the Arts, Stuart, Florida, January 14 - March 1 1994.
"Fierce! NYC," PS122 Gallery, New York, 21 June - 30 June
"Fierce! NYC," PS122 Gallery, New York, 21 June - 30 June
"Water Works," Ed Thorp Gallery, New York, May-June
1994-1995
"Bodies Under Fire," Tyler Gallery, Elkins Park, Pennsylvania, November 16 - January 13 (brochure)
"Bodies Under Fire," Tyler Gallery, Elkins Park, Pennsylvania, November 16 - January 13 (brochure)
"Insight," David Beitzel Gallery, New York, June 22 - July 28
1995
"Narrative," James Graham and Sons Inc, New York, November 9 - December 23
1996
"Arts Communities, Aids Communities: Realizing the Archive Project," Boston Center for the Arts, February-March
"Changing Horizons: Landscape on the Eve of the Millennium," Katonah Museum of Art, Katonah, NY, 28 July - 29 September
"Innovation: American Art of Today from the Misumi Art Collection," Kawamura Memorial Museum of Art, Kawamura, Japan, 14 September - 4 November (catalogue)
1996-1997
"A Living Testament of the Blood Fairies," Artists Space, 9 November-4 January (curated by Frank Moore, Sur Rodney Sur, and Geoff Hendricks; catalogue)
1998
"Pollution," Gian Ferrari Arte Contemporanea, Milan, 22 January-7 March (catalogue)
"Salon: Selections from the Archive Project," National Arts Club, New York, February
"Wishful Thinking," James Graham and Sons, New York, 16 July-11 September
"Summer exhibition," Debs and Co., New York, 9-31 July
"Sea Change," The Parrish Art Museum, Southampton, NY, 13 September-15 November (catalogue)
1998-1999
"The Choice [Aaron Cobbett; Michael Combs]," Exit Art, New York, 14 November-2 January (curated by Frank Moore)
"After Nature," Herter Art Gallery, University of Massachusetts Amherst, 1 December -22 January (catalogue)
1999
"Twenty Years of the Grenfell Press," Paul Morris Gallery, New York, 8 July - August
1999-2000
"Bodies of Resistance," Organized by Visual AIDS in collaboration with Real Art Ways, curated by Barbara Hunt, Real Art Ways, Hartford's Center for Contemporary Culture, Hartford, Connecticut, 1 December, 1999 - 30 January, 2000; KNSA Gallery, Durban, South Africa, July 2000
"I'm Not Here: Constructing Identity at the Turn of the Century," Curated by Sean Mellyn and Jonathan VanDyke, Susquehanna Art Museum, Harrisburg, PA, 2 December 1999 - 24 February 2000 (catalogue)
2000
"1999 Drawings," Alexander and Bonin, New York, 11 December 1999- 22 January 2000
"Arte Americana; Ultimo Decennio," Museo d'Arte della Citta di Ravenna, Ravenna, 8 April - 25 June 2000 (catalogue)
"Post Pop," Curated by Jonathan VanDyke, The Susquehanna Art Museum, Project Room, Harrisburg, PA, 7 June 2000 - 30 June 2000
"Paradise Now," Curated by Marvin Hieferman and Carole Kismaric, Exit Art, New York, 9 September - 28 October 2000
2000-2001
"Art on Paper 2000," Weatherspoon Art Gallery, The University of North Carolina at Greensboro, 19 November 2000 - 14 January 2001 (catalogue)
"1989," Curt Marcus Gallery, New York, 30 November 2000 - 6 January 2001
2001
"Bugs, Bugs, Bugs...," Pace Prints, New York, 30 July - 7 September 2001
"Green on Greene," Sperone Westwater, New York, 1 November – 15 December 2001 (Catalogue)
"Postcards from the Edge," Sara Meltzer Gallery, 18 November 2001
2002
"Rapture: Art's seduction by fashion since 1970," Barbican Art Gallery, London, 10 October –31 December
2003
"The Buddhism Project: Art, Buddhism, and Contemporary Culture," Newhouse Center for Contemporary Art at Snug Harbor, Staten Island
"Genomic Issue(s): Art and Science," Graduate Center Art Gallery, City University of New York, New York City, February 25 - April 2003.
Writings on Art by Frank Moore
"Options and Alternative," essays on Richard Serra and Robert Breer for exhibition catalogue (New Haven, CT: University Art Gallery Yale, 1974)
"On Taste," Tracks magazine, 1976.
"George Negroponte," Arts Magazine, November 1976.
"Better Homes and Gardens," New Observations Magazine, no. 21, 1983.
"Paint by Number," essay to accompany an exhibition held at Christminster Gallery, New York, 1985.
"Offstage Attitudes," essay to accompany the exhibition held at Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln enter, New York as part of the Serious Fun! Festival, July-August 1990.
"The Archive Project: A Large Vision," in Arts/Aids Communities (New York: Visual Aids, 1996), pp. 22-23.
"Something's Coming," Paradise Now, The Tang Teaching Museum and Art Gallery, Saratoga Springs, NY, 2000, pp. 26-29.
Scope and Content Note
The Frank Moore papers contain a wide range of materials relating to his life and career as an artist. Materials include sketchbooks, notebooks, collections of his own and other artists' announcements and invitations. Also included is a wide variety of source materials particularly research materials for Moore's artistic output. Photographs, personal and administrative correspondence, and materials relating to the collaborative filmworks "Beehive" and "Miller's Wife" are also included as well as Moore's library, and some personal and family artifacts.
The Frank Moore Papers are organized into ten series
Series I: Notebooks consists primarily of the artist's sketchbooks and notebooks but also includes some of his date books.
Series II: Art Files is divided into four subseries, containing files which document Moore's art career, administrative materials, related but miscellaneous notes and papers and materials describing other artists' work and careers.
Series III: Correspondence and Manuscripts includes letters and postcards written to Moore as well as some manuscripts. The series is organized into four subseries: Subseries A: Last Name, Subseries B: First Name Only, Subseries C: Miscellaneous, Illegible or Unidentified, and Subseries D: Manuscripts.
Series IV: Source Material contains visual material Frank Moore used for inspiration, research and as source material for his artwork. The contents are arranged in seven subseries: magazines, catalogues, images, articles, photographs, books and ephemera.
Series V: Beehive includes all materials from the production of Frank Moore and Jim Self's collaborative film "Beehive" as well as the Boston Ballet production. The series is divided into eight subseries containing the production elements for the film, technical notations and lab related paperwork, production materials corresponding to the film "Beehive", production materials corresponding to the ballet production, and promotional materials and artifacts. Subseries A: Film Production Elements and Subseries B: Technical Notations and Lab Related Documentation are organized chronologically by unique object identification number. Subseries C: Film Production Materials, Subseries D: Ballet Production Materials, Subseries E: Promotional Materials, and Subseries F: Artifacts are organized alphabetically. Subseries G: Video Recordings - Access Copies, and Subseries H: Film - Access Copies are organized chronologically.
Similarly, Series VI: Miller's Wife includes all materials from the production of Frank Moore and Jim Self's unfinished collaborative film "The Miller's Wife". The series is divided into five subseries composed of film, technical notations and lab related paperwork, production materials, promotion materials and artifacts. Subseries A: Film and Subseries B: Technical Notations and Lab Related Documentation are arranged chronologically by unique object identification number. Subseries C: Production Materials, Subseries D: Promotional Materials and Subseries E: Artifacts are organized alphabetically. Subseries F: Video Recordings - Access Copies, and Subseries G: Film - Access Copies are organized chronologically.
Series VII: Miscellaneous Video and Audio contains media materials unrelated to either Beehive or The Miller's Wife. Subseries A contains access copies for video and audio material. Subseries B contains the original media material. Subseries C contains production information.
Series VIII: Artifacts and Objects contains items relating to Frank Moore's life and artwork. The series is divided into three subseries. Subseries A: Personal artifacts includes objects such as x-rays. Subseries B: Art Implements and Artifacts includes materials such as paint brushes. Subseries C: Miscellaneous includes objects such as the original AIDS ribbons.
Series IX: Juvenalia and Family Memorabilia contains items relating to Frank Moore's life before his art career and significant family items. This series includes among other things a year book and diploma as well as birth and death announcements.
Finally, Series X: Printed Materials contains items from Frank Moore's personal library including books, newspapers, magazines and art catalogues. Materials are organized alphabetically by author last name where available or alphabetically by title.
Arrangement
For the most part, materials are organized alphabetically and chronologically, except for production elements in Series V and VI which are organized sequentially by unique object ID.
Series I: Notebooks
Series II: Art Files
Series III: Correspondence and Manuscripts
Series IV: Source Material
Series V: Beehive
Series VI: Miller's Wife
Series VII: Miscellaneous Video and Audio
Series VIII: Artifacts and Objects
Series IX: Juvenalia and Family Memorabilia
Series X: Printed Materials
Oversize Materials - Series I: Notebooks
Oversize Materials - Series II.A: Frank Moore Clippings, Exhibition Announcements, Press, etc.
Oversize Materials - Series II.C: Frank Moore Administrative
Oversize Materials - Series II.D: Other Artist Art Files
Oversize Materials - Series III.A: Correspondence
Oversize Materials - Series IV.A: Magazines
Oversize Materials - Series IV.B: Catalogues and Manuals
Oversize Materials - Series IV.C: Clippings, Articles and Subject Files
Oversize Materials - Series IV.D: Images
Oversize Materials - Series IV.E: Photographs
Oversize Materials - Series IV.F: Ephemera
Oversize Materials - Series IV.G: Books
Oversize Materials - Series V.D: Production Materials, Boston Ballet and Cornell University Theater
Oversize Materials - Series V.E: Promotional Materials
Oversize Materials - Series V.F: Artifacts
Oversize Materials - Series VI.C: Miller's Wife Production Materials
Oversize Materials - Series VIII.A: Personal Items
Oversize Materials - Series VIII.B: Art Implements and Artifacts
Oversize Materials - Series VIII.C: Miscellaneous